[Music]
this is Teachers talk radio at the BET
show hi everyone uh we're at the bat
show back again um with a really amazing
interview with Jason who's come over for
a quick chat um Jason do you want do you
want to you've probably been asked this
a million times in a million different
interviews but do you want to introduce
yourself a little bit just for people
snap firstly Tom thank you so much for
having me here on um teachers radio and
one of the um I get ask that question a
lot so the easiest way to explain it is
um I try and be a
professor um I teach on stuff broadly
speaking on social justice issues uh
particularly in education Society more
broadly what thank you for that and
please listeners look him up you know I
mean you've got time you sat at home
watching this song just click anyway um
I wanted to ask you you know you've
you've done a lot of interviews what do
you wish an interviewer would have asked
you in one of those interviews that they
never have oh my God that's a great
question also sorry teachers talk radio
you got that he nailed
it they're giving professorships to
anyone now hly um so the one question I
wish someone would ask me about uh music
okay in particular the '90s yeah in
particular guitar music yeah that's why
we someone would ask me an interview
well tell me about something in 90s I
want to know well my view on the '90s is
is the Golden Age it was the Golden Age
it was the last great decade in my
opinion even though at the beginning of
the ' 90s I was five at the end of it I
was 15 but I do there's two decades I
wish I was an adult in the' 60s and the
'90s so there two decades I wish I was
an adult in because I just think it just
seemed like everything was amazing at
that time in terms of music and like the
cultural impact yeah um so that that
that's kind of a question I like to be
asked um but the things I get asked
about are actually important things not
things that I have we're going to
downgrade that
significantly what so well come on just
tell us like one or two bands that you
like from the 90s come on um okay so
Oasis some my favorite band um but I I
knew that I did though um but they don't
get enough respect but ocean color scene
I think an unbelievable bands um Sol
Hill's finest and they don't get they
don't get enough respect but I think
they're an unbelievable band and I think
um Simon is amazing songwriter amazing
songwriter but it doesn't I don't think
they get the respect that they deserve
but and also um supported ouris at
newith which a lot of people often
forget in 96 yes they did they did right
honestly we will talk teaching now just
for a bit so um what I'd like to know is
if you were sat down now with say in a
room with 50 teachers which you
sometimes are um what do you what do you
want teachers to do more or less on than
they are currently doing I mean
obviously it's not your place to say do
I don't mean it in terms of you must do
this but if you had you know 50 captive
teachers in the audience and you said
look I've really like it of teachers did
a bit more of this and a bit less of
this what would those things been so I I
haven't been part of the teaching
fraternity I I was I was previously a
secondary school teacher the one thing
that I
um the national
curriculum over the last 13 years shall
we say 14 years is has been slightly
problematic but what we do have which is
very different to a lot of national
curriculums broadly speaking across
Europe and around the world we have a
lot of autonomy and flexibility in terms
of what we want to do and I guess in the
classroom space what I would love is for
teachers to take more risks can you
bring play into the classroom space can
you do mean I think there's so much
hidden curriculum stuff that we could do
more of and because there's so much
based on kind of metrics kpis and all
those things teachers are under so much
duress and pressure it means that
actually but there is almost a scare
mongering around what they have to do I
mean we've seen some really tragic cases
of what this is ultimately ended up
being and I guess how do you bring that
playfulness into the classroom space um
it should be an exp an experimental
playground and I I don't always feel
like teachers are given the support from
their senior leaders to just kind of
Express themsel you know utilize the
fullest range of their toolkit so I'd
love teachers to do that more because I
think teachers constrained I think
they're so creative and by their very
nature pedagogically speaking they have
to be but they're so constrained in what
they can do and I I wanted to be
Unleashed did you have any creative
teachers when you were growing up I
wouldn't say so if I'm being honest uh
they're quite rare aren't they really
does outside the box no and and
pedagogically speaking like you know
teachers are
probably they often air on a side of
kind of risk you know being you know
taking being risk averse
um not because they want to but because
they're made to um so I I think we're
living in a stage now where people do
have a bit more autonomy than they
actually realize sometimes um and a lot
of those risks are often taken by early
career teachers this is teacher
radi be career teachers given the NT
rations as well but I do think it's
something that I really try and
encourage teachers to do but don't be
scared to take you know it's it's a
playground like teachers should be
allowed to get things wrong in the
classroom it is a learning space do you
ever do you ever get impostor syndrome
doing the things that you do cuz I you
know I was watching an interview the
other day with you and um I think it was
Channel 4 I think it was Channel 4 yeah
the one I was watching things like that
do you do you manage to be yourself in
the public Arena and I suppose my my
next question is a lot of teachers
suffer impostor syndrome whether that be
as teachers in the classroom whether
that be
in life in general a lot of them have
things they want to do you've just said
it you know taking risks in the class
was the same thing number one do you
suffer from it number two how do you
manage it number three what would your
advice be to people who have that yeah I
mean um that's a great question that's a
question I'm asked quite often that's a
great question damn I was hoping for
more like you know Oasis style I know I
know you're doing pretty
um I don't suffer from impostor syndrome
no um and I always encourage other
people not to eat either and the reason
why I say that is because um my belief
is you are where you're supposed to be
and we should always instill people
their aspiration to be where they want
to be so once you arrive at that point
it's not a really good use of energy to
be kind of asking yourself where you
whether you're good enough or you
deserve to be there you're there and
it's a better a better investment of
energy is to figure out how you're going
to stay there and how you're going to
maintain the level required to be there
that's a better use of energy than
questioning yourself you're there
because you deserve to be there and um
it's something that I encourage all
people to think like um and it stems
from
um a confidence that I I believe
everybody has a purpose everybody has
something that they are great at and
when they're able or they're fortunate
to be opportunity to harness that Focus
your energies on harnessing that and
making that the best and being the best
you can be um not questioning whether
that you deserve or whether you're good
enough to be somewhere or not um and
there is a time for reflection and being
self-deprecating um but I don't think
it's useful to kind of question like am
I good enough to be doing this you're
always good enough to be doing this um
you've got one question use that
question for something else like that
question might be did I do did I execute
this as well as I could have done today
what kind of things can I do differently
to ensure that next time I'm in that
situation I execute a lot better to bet
you know I always feel like you allowed
one question Jason what's the question
take loads of feedback from people but
you've got one question to ask yourself
and that question shouldn't
be am I good enough to be here yeah my
last cuz I I want to you know let you go
very shortly so my last question was
going to be the education system in the
UK we've already touched on this a
little bit but what would your hopes be
for the future and and it doesn't have
to be a hope it could be a prediction
you know could be what's going to happen
seen AI this is an ed Tech show the bat
show but you know what are what are your
hopes and what are your predictions for
the future for education system in the
UK and maybe you know outside of the UK
but what the UK specifically yeah I
guess my my hopes for the education
system in the UK is that um we
engage in a way that truly embodies
inclusivity I think the range of pupils
and students that we meet in educational
spaces now is so broadly different
from 5 10 15 20 years ago I think the
the Modern Age The New Age teacher has
to be a s Army pen knife they got to be
able to do a bit of everything and they
always had to do it before but the
implements and the instruments they use
now have to be a little bit sharper than
they once was not that they were blunt
before but they has to be even sharper
now because children are facing a
complex range of issues in relation to a
complex society society's become more
complex economically politically
speaking just generally speaking so I
think what it
requires is really people to kind of
think about how we engage people in
different ways to really think about
diversity as a hugely important asset in
our Arsenal as Educators as pedagog
people who are engaged and invested in
the promise of education and it goes
back to what I've always believed the
purpose of education is prepare people
to set their place in society and what
we need to do as Educators is people
that talk kit to be able to to navigate
a multicultural multi-ethnic multi-
diverse
Society deeply inspiring stuff thank you
ever so much thank you so so much I'm so
grateful great person so thank you and
yeah this will be out in the podcast
soono this is Teachers talk radio at the
BET
show